Guide to the Beach Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Beach Family Papers
1858-1961
RG 60
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(15 boxes)
The papers document various aspects of the lives of brothers David Nelson Beach and Harlan Page Beach, including their student days at Yale (1868-1878), Harlan's work in North China (1883-1890), David's work as a clergyman and with the Anti-Saloon League while in Cambridge, Minneapolis and Denver. David Nelson Beach, 1848-1926, was a prominent Congregational clergyman in Cambridge, Massachusetts, Minneapolis, Minnesota and Denver, Colorado and was active in temperance reform. He was president of Bangor Theological Seminary from 1903-1921. Harlan Page Beach, 1854-1933, was a missionary to China under the American Board from 1883-1890. He was professor of missions at Yale Divinity School from 1905-1921 and librarian of Yale's Day Missions Library from 1911-1925.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology of David Nelson Beach
1848 Nov 30 Born in South Orange, N.J., son of Joseph Wickliff and Mary Angeline (Walkley) Beach
1865-1868 Golden Hill Institute, Bridgeport, Ct.
1868-1872 Yale University, B.A. 1872. Class poet. New Haven correspondent, New York Tribune
1872-1873 Assistant city editor, New York Tribune
1873-1876 Yale Divinity School, B.D.
1876-1879 Pastor of Pawcatuck Congregational Church, Westerly, R.I.
1878 Married Lilian Tappan who became the mother of Dorothea, John, Joseph, and David Nelson Jr. before her death June 30, 1902
1879-1884 Pastor of Congregational Church, Wakefield, Mass.
1884-1896 Pastor of Prospect Street Church, Cambridge, Mass.
1896-1898 Pastor, Plymouth Congregational Church, Minneapolis, Minn.
1896 D.D. Western Reserve University
1899-1902 Pastor of First Congregational Church, Denver, Colo.
1903 Married Dora Freeman who died March 14, 1915
1903-1921 President and Professor of Sacred Rhetoric, Bangor Theological Seminary
1916 Married Ellen Olive Walkley (his cousin).
1921-1926 Pastor-at-large, residing in Guilford and Southington, Ct.
1926Oct 18 Died in Southington, Ct.
Beach was active in temperance work and in work for church unity. He was a member of the Liberal Congress of Religion. His published works included: The Newer Religious Thinking and The Annie Laurie Mine.
Chronology of Harlan Page Beach
1854 Born in South Orange, N.J., son of Joseph Wickliff and Mary Angeline (Walkley) Beach
1870,1871 Worked in Plantsville, Conn. as a bookkeeper
1871 Entered Phillips Academy, Andover, Mass.
1878 B.A. Yale University
1883 B.D. Andover Theological Seminary
1883-1890 Missionary in North China under the American Board, with his wife Lucy Ward Beach.
1901 M.A. (hon.) Yale
1905-1914 Professor of the Theory and Practice of Missions, Yale.
1911-1925 Librarian, Day Missions Library, Yale
1913 D.D. Amherst College
1914-1921 Willis James Professor of the Theory and Practice of Missions, Yale
1921-1933 Professor Emeritus
1933 Mar 4 Died in Florida
Scope and Contents
Rather than providing complete documentation of the lives and work of David Nelson Beach and Harlan Page Beach, the papers of this collection highlight certain aspects of their lives while leaving others untouched. The college years at Yale of both David and Harlan are well documented through letters and diaries. David's career as a prominent Congregational clergyman is traced through correspondence and newspaper clippings up until the year 1903, when he became president of Bangor Theological Seminary. Regular letters to family members document the period when Harlan and his wife Lucy were missionaries in China. Extensive information regarding Beach family relationships and history is available in the collection.
The larger portion of the papers in this collection are related to David Nelson Beach, with only several folders of family correspondence and one item of general correspondence relating to Harlan. Harlan's work as a professor of missions at Yale is touched upon only in a bound volume of letters from former students. No material related to David's work as president of Bangor Theological Seminary is available in this collection.
The first series, Correspondence dates from 1863 to 1961 and is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. The General Correspondence of David Nelson Beach documents his connection with the Liberal Congress of Religion and the American Anti-Saloon League and includes letters from Henry Cabot Lodge, Charles F. Thwing and Henry Clay Trumbull.
The Diaries and Journals of Series II date from the Beaches' student days, 1862 to 1876, and from a trip to Europe taken by David in 1885.
The writings of David Nelson Beach in Series III date from 1862 to 1909 and include many compositions and poems written while a student. The series also contains two items related to mission work which were written by Harlan Page Beach, and one essay related to Congregationalism which was written by David Nelson Beach, Jr. in 1957.
The Personal Items and Memorabilia of Series IV date from 1858 to 1919. The series contains primarily biographical material relating to David Nelson Beach, newspaper clippings, printed material, school reports and so forth. Reviews and correspondence related to his published writings are also in this series.
The Photographs of Series V include one folder of portraits of David and Harlan and several folders of photographs from the travels of Harlan and his wife in Africa, India and the Far East.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1863-1961, n.d.
II. Diaries, Journals, 1862-1885
III. Writings, 1860-1957
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1858-1919
V. Photographs, 1872-1898, n.d.
Congregational churches -- United States; Missions -- China; Missions; Religious education; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Clergy; Educators; Librarians; Missionaries; Beach, David Nelson, 1848-1926; Beach, Harlan P. (Harlan Page), 1854-1933; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924; Thwing, Charles Franklin, 1853-1937; Trumbull, H. Clay (Henry Clay), 1830-1903; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; Anti-saloon League of America; Liberal Congress of Religion; Yale University. Divinity School
- Correspondence, 1863-1961, n.d.; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - David Nelson Beach
      - With parents and sisters, 1863-1896, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
      - With Harlan P. Beach/Lucy W. Beach, 1864-1877 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
      - With Harlan P. Beach/Lucy W. Beach, 1880-1901, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - With aunts/uncles/cousins, 1860-1903, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
      - With Lilian Tappan Beach, 1878-1897 (Box 2, Folder 18-22)
      - With Lilian Tappan Beach, 1898-1901, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
      - With Dora Freeman Beach, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - With his children, 1888-1901 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Lilian Tappan Beach:
      - With her children, 1896,1897,1902,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Letters to family during trip to Europe, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Letters to family during trip to Europe, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - With mother/aunts/cousins/sister, 1894-1897,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Harlan Page Beach / Lucy Ward Beach
      - With family members, 1871,1877-1884 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
      - With family members, 1885-1933, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 35-42)
    - Correspondence Regarding J. W. Beach Estate:
      - re. J. W. Beach estate, 1891-1906, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43-50)
  - General Correspondence
    - David Nelson Beach
      - Correspondence, 1864-1896 Feb (Box 5, Folder 51-63)
      - Correspondence, 1896 Mar-1997 (Box 6, Folder 64-77)
      - Correspondence, 1898 Jan-1901 Jun (Box 7, Folder 78-92)
      - Correspondence, 1901 Jul-1909, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 93-102)
      - re. American Board controversy, 1887 (Box 8, Folder 103)
      - re. American Board controversy, 1900-1905 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Lilian Tappan Beach
      - Correspondence, 1896 Jan-Feb (Box 8, Folder 105)
      - Correspondence, 1896 Mar-1902, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 106-111)
    - Harlan P. Beach
      - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 9, Folder 112)
- Diaries, Journals, 1862-1885; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The diaries and journals are arranged chronologically within two categories:
  A. Diaries and journals of David Nelson Beach (1862-1870, 1874, 1885)
  B. Diaries of Harlan Page Beach (1870-1876)
  - Diaries: DNB, 1862-1870, 1874 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Journal of trip to Europe: DNB, 1885 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Diaries: HPB, 1870, 1872-1876 (Box 10, Folder 116)
- Writings, 1860-1957; Series III
  - David Nelson Beach
    - Writings, 1860-1909 (Box 11, Folder 117-127)
    - Writings, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 128-131)
  - Harlan Page Beach
    - Writings, 1927, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - David Nelson Beach, Jr.
    - Writings, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 132)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1858-1933; Series IV
  - DNB: Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - Miscellaneous
      - Autobiographical, biographical, 1871-1902,n.d. (Box 13, Folder 133)
      - Church-related notices, 1888-1902 (Box 13, Folder 134)
      - Notes, printed material, 1858-1901,n.d. (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Reviews, correspondence re. his writings, 1892,1893, 1903 (Box 13, Folder 136)
      - School reports, 1868-1871 (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Newspaper clippings
      - Biographical and Church-related, 1872-1895 (Box 13, Folder 138)
      - Biographical and Church-related, 1896 (Box 13, Folder 139)
      - Biographical and Church-related, 1897-1902 (Box 13, Folder 140)
      - General subjects, 1870-1898,n.d. (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Printed material
      - Biographical and Church-related, 1876-1883,n.d. (Box 13, Folder 142)
      - Biographical and Church-related, 1896-1919 (Box 13, Folder 143)
      - General subjects, 1878-1902 (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - Lecture notes taken by DNB
      - Small notebook; notes from Yale College classes, 1872 (Box 14, Folder 157)
      - Notes on Church History; Prof. Fisher, YDS, 1874-1875 (Box 15, Folder 158)
      - Notes on Natural Theology and Doctrinal Theology or Dogmatics; Prof. Harris, YDS, 1873-1874 (Box 15, Folder 159)
      - Notes on Doctrinal Theology or Dogmatics; Prof. Harris, YDS, 1874-1876 (Box 15, Folder 160)
  - Harlan Page Beach
    - "In Memoriam", receipt (Box 15, Folder 145)
    - Scrapbook of letters written to Harlan Page Beach by former students now on the mission field, 1921 (Box Ov1)
  - General Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - Incl. Advertisements and Greek Grammar book and re: Lilian Tappan Beach, 1872-1902,n.d. (Box 15, Folder 146)
- Photographs, 1872-1898,n.d.; Series V
  Portraits of David Nelson and Harlan Page Beach, arranged chronologically, are followed by undated photographs of the Far East, Africa, and India, arranged by geographical area.
  - Portraits, 1872-1898,n.d. (Box 14, Folder 147)
  - Africa (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - Burma (Box 14, Folder 149)
  - China (Box 14, Folder 150)
  - India (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - Japan, Okinawa (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - Korea (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - Thailand (Siam) (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Unidentified (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Unidentified (Box 14, Folder 156)